I'm going to start by talking
a little bit about the history
of mortgage lending.
And then I want to talk
more recently about how we do
commercial real estate finance and then residential real
estate finance.
And then if I have time,
I'm going to try to get into
discussing, I have to open the blackboard here.
I have to, I've never done this.
It's a massive door.
And someone was lecturing about astronomy.
So, I'm going to be
talking about, I'm going to be
talking about real estate finance.
It's really about financial contracts that involve real
estate and that particularly use real estate as collateral.
So, it's a very complicated
history, but I like to put
things in a long-term perspective.
So, the word, I want to start with the word.
The word mortgage.
It actually goes back to Latin, mortuus laudium.
And that means in Latin, death pledge.
Okay?
And then in the Middle
Ages in France, they substituted the
French word for a , and that's,
I don't know how to pronounce it.
That means pledge in French.
And I don't know why they call them death pledges.
That doesn't seem to involve death to me.
But it's in the long history
of these institutions that became important.
So, the Oxford English Dictionary says the
word mortgage entered the English language in 1283.
So, we've got a long history here.
But actually, I can take it back further than 1283.
I was inspired by the research of Yale
historian Valerie Hansen, who has been reading old documents
related to the silk trade.
And her documents are based on a trove
of old documents from the Tang Dynasty in China.
Between the 7th and 10th centuries.
Which reflect loans that were made to finance trade.
So, you had people going back and forth from
the Middle East to China with silk and other items.
And they needed financing for the trade.
So, she reads these old documents in Chinese.
And I was looking over her work a
little bit to see whether they had mortgage loans.
She says that in China, they didn't seem
to, at least if I'm getting her generalities right,
they didn't seem to mortgage property.
At least in these documents.
But she says that among these documents
are some, they weren't all in Chinese,
because they were trading between
China and many other countries.
So, she found some in the Sogdian language.
Usually, she reads all these languages.
It's an ancient language of what's modern day Iran.
And it's a dead language.
It died out in the 9th century.
But she finds some Sogdian
documents that look like mortgages.
So, some people borrowed money for the silk trade.
And they would mortgage their property.
Or, they're slaves.
You could mortgage slaves.
It's an awful thought.
And then the contracts would additionally say that you
were obligated to maintain the property or the slaves.
I guess that meant feed your slaves, keep them healthy.
But those were mortgages from the,
well, over a thousand years ago.
And so, it's a very old institution.
But I think it's formed its modern form more recently.
It became a well-known term for the
general public, maybe in the late 18th century.
I was trying to confirm that.
I'm interested in history just out of, I don't
know, just a passion for understanding origins of things.
So, I looked up mortgage.
I looked up in some, on ProQuest
to find old, what were they talking about?
And I found an article
in the Hartford Current dated 1778.
Actually, it wasn't an article.
It was an ad that someone took out.
And I think it's kind of revealing of
what the mortgage market looked like in 1778.
So, we here in Connecticut have, did
you know this, the oldest newspaper in America?
That's the Hartford Current.
So, a man by the name of Elisha Cornwell
took out an ad in the Hartford Current in 1778.
And he explains in the ad that he
lent money as a mortgage on somebody's farm.
Actually, he sold it.
Actually, he sold his farm and was asked,
instead of taking the money right up front,
he mortgaged the farm so that, he
sold it for 800 pounds to another farmer.
And the farmer was promising to pay him.
And if he didn't pay him,
he should get back the farm.
The farmer subsequently sold the
farm, did he mortgage it again?
He mortgaged the same farm for 880 pounds.
So, he's made 80 pounds profit.
It would all be fine and good, except
he still hadn't paid back the first mortgage.
And then the guy mortgaged it again for 1,000 pounds.
And Mr. Cornwell is protesting, hey, you didn't
pay me for the farm in the first place.
So, you don't own the farm.
How are you mortgaging it multiple times?
So, he said, I thought I better put an ad in the
newspaper, so that any subsequent victims of this farmer would be warned.
So, that's the end of the ad.
He said, this is my
farm, because he didn't pay me.
But this shows how undeveloped
mortgage institutions were in 1778.
Because he had to put an
ad in the newspaper to explain that.
The problem was, he didn't pay the farmer.
The problem was that nobody had
any systematic way of representing title.
The farmer who bought it from, who
supposedly bought it from Mr. Cornwell really didn't.
And nobody would know that.
You know, he could fool people.
So, I think that's partly why you
didn't see so many mortgages in those days.
Because you couldn't, the law wasn't clear.
The institutions didn't know.
The institutions were not clear about property.
And so, you couldn't really do a mortgage business, if you couldn't
find out whether the guy mortgaging the farm really owned it or not.
And so, it wasn't until the late 19th century
that government started to get property law, rights to property.
And so, it wasn't until the late 19th century that government started to get
property sufficiently advanced that we could develop a big national or international market in mortgages.
So, an important step is in Germany in
1872, or Prussia, the government created a Grundbuch law.
That created a law.
That created a system for Prussia that established in
a book, a central book, who owns what exactly.
That was in 1872.
And in 1897, they made it a national German institution.
Still, the United States did not
have a Grundbuch at the time.
It wasn't, it developed throughout the 20th century.
It developed throughout the 20th century.
And it developed throughout the 20th century in different countries of the world that
property rights would be clear enough that one could do a mortgage lending business.
So, that's why I think mortgage lending
has really taken off in the 20th century.
Hernando de Soto, who's a Peruvian economist, wrote a
book a few years ago called Mystery of Capital.
And it's about the developing world.
And he argued in that book that property rights, the problems that we just heard
about from the Hartford Courant, are still very big and alive around the world today.
That you can't easily establish who owns what
in many or most countries of the world.
So, that's a problem.
That's why we don't see mortgage finance developing there.
You can't make a loan.
You know, if you go to some
small country, you can't make a loan.
You know, if you go to some small town in some
less developed country, you can ask around, who owns this property?
And they'll tell you, you know, that's been in
such and such a family for a long time.
But if you want solid knowledge of that, how do you, you know, if you're
going to base a financial transaction on it, you can't base it just on hearsay, right?
I mean, someone else might have a different opinion.
So, even today, in many countries of the
world, the laws are not developed well enough.
We don't have property rights established well enough.
And we have laws that might inhibit mortgages.
For example, in many countries, if you give a mortgage on a property, in other words, you lend
on a property, then, and the person doesn't pay, you're supposed to be able to seize the property, right?
But if the court system doesn't function well,
or if it's complicated, then you can't pay.
And if the court system doesn't function well, or if it's kind of left-leaning and, you know,
supporting the rights of the person living in the home, you might not be able to get it.
Or it might take you 10 years to
get the guy thrown out of the house.
Now, it seems cruel to throw someone out
of a house who doesn't pay on their mortgage.
But you have to think
of the other side of it.
If we don't throw them out of the
house, no one's going to make a mortgage.
You have to be able to get the house, right?
That's the idea of a mortgage.
If the guy doesn't pay, the lender gets the house.
And so, I think there's a general process of development, improving the definition of
property rights and improving the ability of lenders to get the property if it fails,
which accounts for the advance of mortgage
lending in the 20th and 21st century.
So, that's my long history of mortgage lending.
But I want to get into some specific instances.
I said I would start with commercial real estate.
And my, before, yeah.
So, and then I'll move to
single-family homes or residential real estate.
And I'm going to talk
now mostly about the United States.
This is too many countries to think about.
One thing about finance is that it tends to develop
a sort of tradition and a sort of standard contract.
It's encouraged by laws and regulators.
You kind of have to do the same sort
of contract that other people are doing in your country.
And I think the standardization is kind of a limitation.
We can't be creative in financing because the public
and the regulators will not be receptive to new things.
Let me talk about some of the
institutions in finance in the United States.
It's natural to start with commercial real estate.
So, you see a lot of buildings around, okay?
My question is, how are they owned?
I don't know whether you think about this.
Who owns these buildings?
Well, in much of the 20th century and
still today, they tend to be owned as partnerships.
Right?
So, real estate partnerships.
Real estate partnerships, which
is different from a corporation.
In a corporation, we talked about that yesterday, you
might sell shares on the stock exchange if it's public.
And it's defined as a legal person.
And it has limited liability so that all the shareholders
don't have to worry about being sued as a result.
But a partnership is different.
And most real estate that's not part of a larger
business is owned in a partnership rather than a corporation.
And the reason is that they're taxed more favorably.
Corporations have to pay a corporate profits tax.
Okay, they're double taxed.
You as an individual pay an income tax.
And your corporation pays a corporate income tax.
Or a corporate profits tax.
So, you're taxed twice.
If you incorporate yourself or you set up some friends
to do business in a corporation, you get taxed twice.
So, you don't like that.
And obviously, you try to avoid that.
The way to avoid it
is not to have a partnership.
Not to have a corporation, but a partnership.
And you have to.
The law allows you to form partnerships.
To own a building, say.
So, you're building, I don't know how, 360 State Street.
This is a new building that
just went up in New Haven.
Do you know this building?
The biggest construction.
Does anyone know who owns it?
It's probably a partnership.
I haven't investigated that.
Or it's called a direct participation program.
So, the partnership is,
an investment that is offered only to accredited investors.
It's not generally available to the general public.
And what is an accredited investor?
The Securities and Exchange Commission takes it
upon itself to define who are accredited investors.
That don't need the protections of the SEC.
Basically, accredited investors are,
wealthy people.
And it's defined in the SEC laws,
who is accredited.
You have to have at least a million dollars.
Or minimum income.
And so, if you are an accredited investor,
you can invest in a DPP.
Alright?
And then, the income of the property,
flows through to you as your personal income.
It's not corporate income.
So, it's taxed only once.
You think about that.
Well, why would anyone form a corporation?
Because, I don't want to be taxed twice.
So, why don't we do all business as a DPP?
As a partnership.
The problem is, that the government
doesn't want you to do that.
And so, they have rules
about what can form a partnership.
And so,
one of the rules is that
they have to have a limited life.
So, a corporation goes on forever.
And it derives a lot of its
value from the fact that it lives forever.
There's no end date.
So, we talked about that when
I brought up the first real corporation,
the Dutch East India Company.
The reason it got so valuable is,
people could see that this was growing.
It's the first multinational.
It was this huge company.
It had all kinds of
deals and alliances and business arrangements.
And no one wanted that to end.
The value came in the growth prospects for that.
But a DPP has to end.
So, what you do is,
it's well designed for a building.
You buy the building and you depreciate
it over the life of the contract.
And then there's an end date.
And at the end date, you
sell the building to someone else.
And then you close down the DPP.
You don't hear about these partnerships as much.
You hear about companies, corporations all the time.
You don't hear about DPPs, first of
all, because they don't get so big.
They're typically one building, 360 state, for example.
And it only lasts for however, 10, 20 years.
And then it's gone.
It might have a different name.
And it doesn't get advertised to the public,
because it's not available to the public.
And they can't go around trying
to bring you in as an investor,
because they have to verify
that you're an accredited investor.
So, it tends to be a project for wealthy people.
Now, I mentioned that corporations have limited liability.
Partnerships do not, in general.
But you can have a partnership
that involves two classes of partners.
There's general partner that runs the business.
And does not have limited liability.
In other words, if the
business goes bad and loses money,
the general partner can get sued.
But there are other partners called limited partners.
And they have to be passive investors.
And they have limited liability.
So, what often happens is a DPP is
created by someone who understands and knows real estate.
Let's get 360 State Street built.
And you're going to know that eventually,
because once they open, they're going to open
a supermarket in the first floor of 360 State.
And I'll bet some of you will be over there.
Because it will be the
closest supermarket to Yale University.
But it's all part of somebody's plan.
There was some general partner who thought up this structure
and got limited partners in.
And is running the, managing the building.
And has a manager for the building.
And has a plan and a closeout plan.
The building won't disappear, but
they'll sell it to someone else.
I really don't know the financing structure of 360 State.
But I'm just pointing out,
it's likely what's happened there.
So, that has been the modern structure of real estate.
And if they mortgage the building, it would be,
the DPP would mortgage the
building on behalf of the partners.
So, real estate finance in the United States,
I might as well write it down.
DPP is a direct participation program
in the profits of real estate.
And it's direct in the
sense that you, as an investor,
are participating directly in the profits of it.
You are a partner.
You're not a shareholder.
Okay.
The DPPs became criticized in the 20th century,
because small investors couldn't access these.
Small investors were confined,
because they weren't accredited.
They weren't big enough or important enough.
They were not allowed to invest in these.
It was supposed to be to protect them.
All right?
I guess.
But how does it protect them?
To subject them to double taxation.
So, it became a cause that,
why in the United States do
we have most of our investors
closed out of these lucrative investment opportunities?
Why can't individuals, basically,
invest in commercial real estate?
And people said,
well, people are supposed to diversify.
They're supposed to hold different kinds of investments.
So, what's the,
why would this be limited to them?
So, Congress in the United States in 1960
created something new called a real,
I think the chalk is weak.
I'm trying to be gentle,
and the chalk can't,
I'm not being rough, am I?
It keeps collapsing.
I'll be very gentle here.
Real estate investment trusts
are, it's abbreviated REITs.
These were created,
in 1960,
by an act of the U.S. Congress.
And it was a democratization,
another example of the democratization of finance.
And I believe it started here in the United States.
Now they are being copied all over the world.
They got off to kind
of a slow start after 1960,
but they have grown dramatically.
And so,
the idea is that we will allow a company to,
well, it would be a trust,
to create investments for the general public,
for small investors,
and they won't be double taxed either.
Okay?
So, a real estate investment trust
has to follow the law,
and then it can invest in buildings.
So, maybe 360 state is owned by a REIT.
I don't know.
But they are not subject to the corporate profits tax.
Now, once again,
once Congress creates a vehicle that's not taxed,
everyone's going to ask,
well, I want my company to be a REIT.
Okay?
So, they had to define it,
so that it isn't generally available.
It's limited to real estate.
So, the law says,
75% of the assets of the company
have to be in real estate or cash.
75% of the income has to be from real estate.
90% of their income must be from real estate,
dividend, interest, and capital gains.
95, this is all, I think, in your textbook, Fibozzi.
95% of the income must be paid out.
And there has to be a long-term holder.
No more than 35% of the income
can be from the sale of properties
held less than four years.
They don't want, you know,
real estate churning companies.
So, if you define all of that,
you've got a REIT.
And so, that invention,
which goes back to 1960,
it's one of those things in finance,
it starts out slowly,
most people don't hear of it,
and then it starts to grow.
And REITs, and now they're everywhere around the world,
but they're not going to be
everywhere, but in many countries we have REITs.
The U.S. REITs grew in a succession of booms.
The first boom was in the late 1960s,
when the interest rates in the United States
rose above deposit ceilings.
There used to be ceilings that the government
imposed on savings banks' deposit rates.
And so, suddenly, the REITs were paying better
than the savings banks,
and the public flocked to them.
There was a second REIT,
which was called the Reit of the Revenue.
There was a second boom
after the tax reform of 1986
eliminated some tax advantages of DPPs and partnerships.
It used to be that the government allowed
generous depreciation allowances for partnerships.
And people would invest in building just as tax dodges.
Because if you're allowed to depreciate the building
very effectively,
you can kind of cook your profits
so that it's not taxable.
And so, people were investing in buildings too much.
The government created a distortion
that encouraged too much investment in DPPs.
So, in 1986, the government made it harder for,
it eliminated a lot of the advantages of partnerships.
And that caused the second REIT boom.
And then, starting in the 1990s,
with the real estate boom,
the public got excited.
The public got excited.
Suddenly, lots of new kinds of REITs appeared.
And REITs that involved specialized properties and the like.
Now they're big.
And everyone talks about them.
But it's interesting to me that it took 50 years
to get as big as they are now.
And again, the theme that I'm recurring here,
recurring theme, a couple of them.
One is that the finance industry
finds it difficult to innovate.
And innovations take many years to happen.
And secondly, that there's a trend
toward the democratization of finance.
That if you go back in history,
you'll find these same mortgages
and partnerships and the like,
but they were limited to
a small number of wealthy people.
And we're moving with the invention of REITs, for example.
More and more people are getting involved.
Okay.
So, that's commercial real estate.
I want to talk now about residential real estate,
which is actually bigger.
There are more houses than there are office buildings
in this country.
Or there's more value in housing.
So, this is bigger.
In the United States,
about two-thirds of households own their own home.
It varies across countries,
but there are many other countries
with similarly high home ownership rates.
And this home ownership is a product of government policy
that encourages mortgage lending.
So, I wanted to talk
a little bit about the history
of mortgage lending
and the history of problems in mortgage lending.
Now, I already took you back to the silk trade
in the Tang Dynasty,
but I'm going to be less so far back now.
We're going to talk about the United States
and the Great Depression.
So, the Great Depression
in the United States
in the 1930s,
after the 1929 stock market crash,
was faced with a severe housing crisis.
Home prices were falling
and people were defaulting on their mortgages
in great numbers.
In fact, the government had to create
what they called a homeowner's loan corporation
to bail people out.
And they ended up bailing out 20%
of American homeowners.
It was a terrible crisis.
So, what was happening?
I'm pointing this out because it's important
in the history of real estate finance.
Before the Great Depression,
mortgages were growing.
But I'll say before the Great Depression,
they tended to be two to five years
and they were balloon payment.
What do I mean by that?
When you bought a house in 1920,
you'd go to a bank
and they would give you a loan
for two to five years.
So, if you bought a house for $10,000,
they would typically lend you half the money.
They'd lend you $5,000.
And the loan would say,
you pay interest every month
until two years has ended
and then you repay the $5,000.
Okay?
And then you could try to get another mortgage.
You come back to us and we'll do it again
if we feel like it.
Okay? That was the deal.
Banks offered that
and it was becoming increasingly common.
When we say a balloon payment,
what we mean is,
it's really big.
Balloons are big.
All right?
So, you're paying monthly interest,
but then in two years,
you got to come up with the whole $5,000.
All right?
But, okay, people thought,
it's all right.
I'll just go back to the bank
or maybe I go to another bank.
You know, I go wherever I want.
And I can borrow $5,000.
Okay?
So, this was the way things were done.
But what happened in the Great Depression?
Two things happened.
The unemployment rate went up to 25%.
A. B.
Home prices fell, in many cases,
by more than a half.
So, if you borrowed $5,000
against a $10,000 home,
your home might be worth only $4,000 now.
So, what do you do now?
You go to a bank.
Okay?
Two years is up.
I got to refinance my mortgage.
I go back to the bank.
And I show up and I say,
A. I'm unemployed and my house is worth $4,000.
The bank says,
you know, no dice.
You're not going to get renewed.
So, what happens?
You're forced to dump your house on the market.
You declare bankruptcy.
You've lost everything.
You've lost your $5,000 down payment.
If you buy a $10,000 home,
you're going to have to pay a $10,000 down payment.
So, you're going to have
to pay a $10,000 down payment.
You're going to have to pay a $10,000 down payment.
So, you're going to have
to pay a $10,000 down payment.
You're going to have to pay a $10,000 down payment.
So, you've lost everything.
You've lost your $5,000 down payment.
You're going to have to pay a $10,000 down payment.
So, if you buy a $10,000 house,
and you borrow $5,000,
then your,
the other side is called your down payment.
So, that's what happened.
It was happening to millions of Americans.
And, so, the Roosevelt administration,
decided that the old kind of mortgage didn't,
there was something wrong with that mortgage.
I was just busy working,
and then I was busy buying.
It came to me,
and it was finally a mortgage.
And now,
I have to pay for it.
So, the Roosevelt administration decided that
the old kind of mortgage didn't, there was something
wrong with that mortgage.
So, in 1934, when Franklin,
it was a year after Franklin
Roosevelt became president, they set up the Federal Housing
Administration, and it specified that, it offered, it
was trying to get lenders
back in to lend to homeowners,
because it was a catastrophe in the country.
I'm not saying right.
So, in order to get
lenders back in, the FHA started
engineering.
They started insuring mortgages.
And that meant that if
you're a mortgage lender, and your
mortgage, the person you lent the money to doesn't repay
you, and the house isn't worth
enough, you can get the house,
but you might lose money, because the house has lost
value, the government will make it up.
So, the government came in with what's called mortgage
insurance.
And at the same time, the government said, all the
mortgages that are insured by the
FHA must be 15 years or
longer.
And so, the U.S. government imposed the long-term mortgage
on the mortgage industry.
And they said, this is better, because the mortgage, and
secondly, it cannot be a balloon payment mortgage.
The government said, you know, this is
really imposing too much on ordinary people, that
they have to come up with a huge
sum of money at the end of the mortgage.
So they required that the mortgages be 15-year amortizing.
Such mortgages had been offered already by some
banks in the United States in the 1920s.
But it was innovative finance,
and too complicated for most people.
They didn't, it never caught on.
Let me understand.
Amortization.
And amortize means to pay down the balance.
So an amortizing mortgage has
no balloon payment at the end.
A 15-year amortizing mortgage has a fixed monthly payment.
You make it every single month.
And at the end, you're done.
You take your spouse out
to dinner, and you say, we've
paid off our mortgage.
We're done.
So there's no family crisis at the end.
So, you have a fixed monthly payment.
Now, the arithmetic of amortizing mortgage is a
little confusing to some people.
And in 1934, it took some education.
But I want to just describe the amortizing mortgage
system.
All right, so we're going
to have a mortgage of maturity
and maturity of the mortgage is in m.
And that's in months.
OK?
So, in 1934, they started out with 15-year mortgages, which
they thought was pretty aggressive.
But by the early 1950s, the FHA was emphasizing 30-year
mortgages.
That's a long time to pay off in your house.
But the idea is, you know, your typical
family, they get married, and they're married, and
they're married.
And they're married.
You didn't.
So, they're married.
You don't have to worry
about having to pay off, you're
married.
And you don't have to
worry about having to pay off.
So, what if they're buying
their first house, they're 25 years
old.
So, let's give them a full
30 years to pay off the mortgage.
They'll be 55.
Kids will be going off to college.
They'll still be working.
That's a comfortable length of time.
Why not give them 30 years?
And we guarantee the interest rate for 30 years.
No surprises.
You just know you have this
monthly payment, and you've got it.
OK, the idea of an amortizing
mortgage is that you have a
fixed payment every month.
You have an interest rate, and
you want to make sure that the
present value of the monthly payments equals the mortgage
balance at the beginning.
So, the initial mortgage balance, that's the amount you
borrowed, has to equal the present discounted value of
all the monthly payments.
What will I call the monthly payment?
Let's call the monthly payment x is the
monthly payment in dollars.
So, the mortgage balance is equal to
x all over r over 12,
where r is the annual interest rate,
times 1 minus 1 all over 1
plus r over 12 to the mth power.
That's just the annuity formula.
OK, so that's the formula that's used in the
mortgage balance.
I'll just use the compute to make sure.
So, I've shown you that formula before.
It's the present value of a
stream of payments equal to x.
Did I write r over 2?
I meant r over 12.
So, what you have to do,
if you are calculating an amortizing
rate, if the person is borrowing the amount, well,
the mortgage balance, and I quote
a rate r per year, I have
to plug that into the present
value formula and find out what
monthly payment x makes the present value equal to the
amount loaned.
Now, that is a little bit of arithmetic that mortgage
lenders would have had trouble doing.
It's not that hard to do, right?
But I have here a page here.
I have a page from a mortgage table.
I found this in the Yale Library.
Can you read that?
This is from a 50-year-old book.
This is before they had computers.
And so, it was too hard to do this calculation.
But I just wanted to,
can you read it in back?
Sort of.
This is for a 10-year mortgage.
I just picked 10 years.
That was uncommon.
I just wanted to show you.
Some people would get shorter mortgages, especially older
people.
You know, if you're 60 years
old, you don't want a 30-year
mortgage.
You probably won't live that long.
So, they did give out shorter mortgages as well.
So, this is a page from
a mortgage book for 10 years, and
this is for 5% mortgage.
So, it shows the monthly payment for $1,000.
If someone's borrowing for $1,000, they're going to get a
If someone's borrowing $5,000, you'd multiply this by 5.
But they show it for around $1,000.
And the monthly payment, it says, monthly payment per $1,000
is $10.61.
So, what they've done is, they've found out, X, $10.61,
is the X that makes this present
value for r equal 5% equal to $1,000.
So, they've done exactly this calculation.
Now, they show the payment schedule.
And the payment every month is $10.61.
But what this table shows
is the breakdown between amortization
and interest.
So, it shows the principle for each month.
So, you borrow at the
beginning, you borrow $1,000 on this
mortgage.
And you're paying $10.61.
And you're paying $10.61 per month.
So, each month, your balance goes down.
This balance column, they subtract.
Well, the question is, how do you figure it out?
You're paying $10.61 per month.
But part of that is interest.
What part of that is interest?
Well, it's 5% divided by 12
of the $1,000 balance at the beginning.
So, your initial interest is $4.17.
So, your principal is the $10.61 minus the interest.
So, then that reduces your balance.
So, the initial interest is $4.17.
The principal is $6.44.
So, the balance is $993.56 after one month.
The next month, they figure what
fraction of your payment is interest
and you're multiplying 5% over
12 times the balance, $993.56.
And then that comes out to be $4.14 interest.
You see, the interest is going to be
going down because you're paying off the loan.
But your payment is fixed.
So, the payment against principal is going up.
So, the first month was $4.17 interest.
The next month is $4.14 interest.
Offsetting that is the first month with
$6.44 being used to pay off your mortgage.
The second month, it's more, $6.47.
And this goes all the way down.
I couldn't show the whole page here.
But here, after six years, six
months, your interest is down to $1.74
because your balance is down to $4.07.61.
And so, your payment of principal is much higher.
So, the reason this table is important is
that people move and they sell their house early.
They don't hold it for the full 10 years.
So, you have to figure out when someone sells his
house after six years, six months, what do they still owe?
Well, they now owe, instead of $1,000, they owe $407.61.
So, that's the idea of a long-term mortgage.
Your interest payments are changing all the time.
Your principal payments are changing all the time.
But your total payment is fixed.
That was an invention, a financial innovation in 1934.
And it is now offered, this
is called a conventional fixed-rate mortgage.
And it's now offered in many countries of the world.
However, there's only two countries where
it's the major kind of mortgage.
The United States and Denmark.
And this is a strange.
Strange thing.
This invention has not caught on around the world.
It's unique to only two countries.
Although, you can get it in other countries.
It's not available in Canada in any number.
I guess you could find it.
But it's not common elsewhere.
Every time I go to a
foreign country, I ask the people there,
why don't you have fixed rates?
And they say, well, we have fixed-rate mortgages.
And I don't necessarily get good answers.
I've been trying to understand why it hasn't caught on.
Then I recently saw that Alastair
Darling, who was under the labor government,
Chancellor, I'm trying to be gentle here.
He was Chancellor of the Exchequer in the United Kingdom
until the Conservative government took over.
And he issued a statement saying that
UK should finally adopt the long-term mortgage.
And the reason, the problem is, is that
any country that doesn't
have a long-term fixed-rate mortgage
runs the risk of falling into the same problem
that the United States did in the Great Depression.
Some kind of crisis like that could mean
that people would lose their homes in great numbers.
So he said he'd like to see the UK get people
borrowing at 10, 20, or even 25 years for their mortgages.
But instead, what happened was
the Conservative government took over.
But there are, you can
in the UK get long-term mortgages.
And I think it's true
in most countries of the world.
They're just not common there.
And it's a bit of a puzzle.
Why is it that only two countries do this generally?
I have a couple of reasons offered why it is.
One of them is that the
general public is resistant to long-term mortgages
because they charge a higher interest.
If the government is going to
guarantee a rate for 30 years,
not the government, the bank, the lender
is going to guarantee it for 30 years,
they're going to have to charge you a higher rate
because that guarantee costs something for them.
And, and,
consumers are resistant to paying the higher rate.
And that's part of the problem.
The other part of the problem is that bank
regulators might not encourage banks to make these loans
because it's risky for banks.
If banks tie their money up for 30 years,
and then they have depositors who
can withdraw their money at any time,
the banks could go under.
If there was ever a run on the
banks, they can't liquidate these mortgages fast at all.
So you need to understand,
you need a coordinated effort of a government
to first make sure the regulators,
the regulators accept these concepts.
It puts some risk on the public,
a possible bailout of the banking system.
But,
and then you have to get past public resistance.
You have to make the public understand
that when you get a fixed rate mortgage,
it's a clean contract.
We have no worries for things like that.
We've been doing this for 30 years.
As opposed to,
there are problems that have sometimes occurred.
In Canada, in 1980,
the government,
the interest rate shot way up.
And we had a kind of a duplicate
of the problem that we saw in the U.S.
People couldn't afford to refinance their mortgages.
And a lot of people lost their homes.
And so it was a big problem.
But they somehow got through that.
And they're not really thinking about
fixed rate mortgages in Canada,
even now today.
So, I wanted to go on
talking about
innovation in finance.
Another very important innovation is
securitization of mortgages.
And government support of mortgage markets.
So, in the United States,
in 1938,
the federal government,
this is also Roosevelt administration,
set up
the Federal
National
Mortgage
Administration.
Which was a government agency,
that would buy mortgages to support the mortgage market.
On Wall Street,
they couldn't pronounce
Federal National Mortgage,
or is it Association?
I'm sorry.
I have administration.
Is it Association?
It's Association,
not administration.
You know what they called it on Wall Street?
They called it Fannie Mae.
That was just
irreverent shortened name
for the association.
It was run by the government.
And, however,
it was in the year
the U.S. government
privatized Fannie Mae.
And it became a private corporation.
So, what did Fannie Mae do?
It would buy mortgages from banks.
They were trying to encourage the mortgage market.
So, a bank would lend money
to someone to buy a house,
and then they're done.
They can't lend any more money,
unless they raise more deposits.
Well, Fannie Mae would buy the mortgage from them.
And they'd have money again to lend again.
And so,
they did this in 1938,
because we were still in the Depression.
And the housing market
was still depressed.
They weren't building homes.
There were lots of unemployed construction workers.
And so,
Roosevelt was just thinking,
how can we stimulate the economy?
And this was one of their ideas.
So, Fannie Mae
was the mortgage finance giant
that was created
in 1968.
And,
I can shut this off here.
So,
in
government created
another Fannie Mae-like
institution.
Its official
name was
Federal Home Loan Mortgage Corporation.
And Wall Street had to invent a name for it.
So,
they called it
Freddie Mac.
They thought,
well, we gave a girl's name to Fannie Mae,
let's give a boy's name.
I guess that's a boy's name.
Now, both of these organizations
call them,
they're both private companies now,
created by the government.
They both use these names officially now.
So,
that's their name now.
Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac.
Freddie Mac was initially different,
because what the government asked Freddie Mac to do
was buy mortgages
and then
repackage them as mortgage securities
and sell them off
with a guarantee, a Freddie Mac
guarantee.
And so, once Freddie Mac
started doing this, Fannie Mae said,
well, can't we do that too?
So, they both do it.
So, what the government had done
is create two private corporations.
You kind of wonder, well,
private corporations,
why did the government even do that?
Freddie Mac, anyone can create.
Remember, we have a corporate law.
I can start my own Freddie Mac,
my own Fannie Mae.
But the government did create them,
well, by privatizing Fannie Mae
and by creating Freddie Mac.
And they are both in the
mortgage securitization business.
So, they would buy from
mortgage originators,
people who lend the money,
they'd buy the mortgages.
In other words, they'd take the IOU from someone,
they'd repackage them into securities,
and sell them off
to the public, with a guarantee
from Fannie or Freddie
that the mortgage,
if there were a default,
the mortgage extra balance
would be made up by Fannie
or Freddie.
Well, they might then, they did then
get other companies
called mortgage insurers to
insure at least part of the
balance. So, it's a complicated financial
agreement. But what we had was
private companies created by the U.S.
government that created
securities for investors that were
guaranteed against defaults.
And based on the,
based on mortgages.
So, the
government then
also stated that these are
private companies and the U.S.
government does not stand behind
them. People started to say,
the government created these two
corporations, and now they're
securitizing and guaranteeing
trillions of dollars of mortgages.
And is this
going to come back and end up being
paid for by the taxpayer?
So, the government
stated clearly, these are
now private corporations. Fannie Mae
started out as part of the government,
but no longer. Now it's a private
corporation, and if Fannie Mae
goes bankrupt, woe betide
anyone who bought their securities.
Because their guarantee is
not backed up by the federal government.
So, people
complained though. They said,
you're saying
that it's not backed up by the federal government,
but do you really mean that?
If Fannie or Freddie goes
bankrupt, will the U.S. government
just let them go under?
Well, the official statement
was, yes, the government will let them go under.
Guess what happened?
Okay.
In 2008,
the real estate market crashed
and we had our first housing crisis.
That was similar to
the Great Depression.
And in that housing crisis,
both Fannie and Freddie
went bankrupt.
Okay? And now,
what do we do? We're in the Bush administration.
Republican. They don't particularly like
bailouts. Okay?
So, you'd think, of course,
George W. Bush would just,
it's the law, right? The federal government's
not going to bail them out?
But then some people said, wait a minute.
You know,
all over the world, people are investing in these,
thinking that, well, Fannie Mae
was created by the U.S. government.
In particular, a lot of Chinese,
those poor innocent Chinese,
were trusting the Americans.
And they put many billions
of dollars into
Fannie Mae. Are you going to go and tell
the Chinese, sorry,
you know, we won't back it?
Well, someone could say, sure,
go tell them that. It's what we've been saying
all along. But then the Chinese
could come back and say, well,
you've been saying that, but nobody believed you.
Everyone knew that that wasn't right.
And you,
the federal government didn't take all the right
steps to make it really clear.
For example, the Wall Street
Journal used to list
Fannie Mae Bonds and Freddie Mac
Bonds in a section of the newspaper
entitled, Government
Securities.
And that's the Wall Street Journal.
That's not the government talking.
But, you know, the U.S.
government should have come in
and told them, no, those aren't
government. So, we poor
innocent Chinese investors,
we read your paper and it said, Government
Securities.
Now, George Bush could have said,
tough luck, you know, you guys, you should
have read the fine print.
But he didn't.
Why not? Because it jeopardizes
too much. If the U.S. government
lets these agencies that it created
go bankrupt, and it lets
all those people all over the world
who invested in those securities,
they're going to be mad, right?
And, you know,
we have a reputation.
The United States is able
to raise so much money from all over
the world because they think
that it's safe here. And if
we just let these fail, it's
not going to look right. So, the
U.S. government took them both under
conservatorship and is paying their
debts, paying off. So,
those did not default. What we've
learned from this lesson is that
you can say a million
times that you're not going to guarantee something.
But when it comes
eventually, you end up guaranteeing it.
I wanted to just say something about other countries
a little bit. Canada
has something like
Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac
called the Canada
Housing and Mortgage Corporation.
So, I'll just talk about other countries.
The Canada
Housing
and Mortgage Corporation.
The Canada
Housing and Mortgage Corporation.
And it was created in
I actually don't have
the year. But it was created
by the government of Canada. And it does work
that resembles FHA
and it resembles
Fannie Mae. But it's
owned by the Canadian government. It's not privatized.
It's owned by the Canadian government. It's not privatized.
And so,
you might say, well, it's the same in Canada.
But the big difference is,
it's smaller. They didn't
let it get as big as Fannie and Freddie.
And so,
it isn't heard as much
from. I was a keynote
speaker at a conference
February 3
that the Financial Times
organized in New York called
Focus on Canada.
And I had to give a talk about Canada
to New York investors.
They told me there were hardly any Canadians
in the audience. What are we doing
here in New York talking about Canada?
Well, it's because the Americans invest
heavily in Canada.
So, I was up talking to all these American
people. And I was looking at
Canada and Canada
banking system.
I said to the group,
you know, Canada and America
are just so similar. I can't see much
of a difference.
The recent financial
Canada didn't have
Fannie and Freddie. It didn't have these housing
problems. But the worldwide
recession hit Canada pretty hard.
And so, I said,
Canada and the U.S. are kind of
like two peas in a pod. That's what I
said. They're so
similar. People like to
make much of differences, but the Canadian
economies just move up and down in lockstep.
And I
also said, Canada was saved
by the oil crisis.
Being an oil exporter. And if it didn't have
oil, it would have been
destroyed by the oil. In 2008, remember
when the oil prices shot up?
But little to my knowledge, there was a
reporter for the Financial Post in Canada
in the audience. And my talk
got reported in the Financial Post.
And then,
I went on their website
and there was blogs, angry blogs
from Canadians.
I don't think it's so insulting to Canada
to say that we're just basically similar.
I didn't,
I don't think it's so
insulting to Canada to say that we're
just basically the same.
But what I'm,
and I'll have to say this for Canada.
They did not get so gung-ho
on supporting mortgages as the United
States did. So, they didn't have
such a big housing bubble
that the U.S. did.
Part of the reason the U.S. had a housing
bubble as big as it did is that
the U.S. government, see these guys
really weren't independent. They were taking
orders from the government. And
the government was telling them
to lease their lending to low income
or to underserved communities.
They wanted, they were promoting
the bubble. And so, Fannie and Freddie
were told to promote
lending to houses during
the real estate bubble that preceded
the crisis. That didn't happen,
at least not so much in Canada.
So, they've had less of a bubble.
But still,
the two countries are
basically very similar.
So, I think we're,
the textbook talks a lot about
mortgage securities.
And there's
major,
I expect you to read this out of Famosi.
I actually
got complaints.
I'll tell you, in past years,
students found this the least enjoyable
part of the readings for this course.
But,
you should know about these things.
So, we have securities
called collateralized
mortgage obligations.
These are
mortgage securities
that hold, they're securities
that are sold off to investors.
And they
hold mortgages.
But, as it's explained in
Famosi,
they will divide them into
separate tranches, or separate
securities
in terms of prepayment
risk.
That is, there's a risk that the mortgages
will be paid off early.
In times when it's adverse to the
investor interest.
So, they would divide up the risks
into different classes of securities.
And some of them were rated
triple A by the rating agencies
because they thought there was almost no
risk to those securities.
And others were rated
different, differently.
And these CMOs
were
sold to investors all over the world.
Another kind of security which
the textbook talks about is a
CDO, which is a
collateralized debt
obligation. And these are issued
to investors.
And they typically hold mortgage securities
as their assets.
Many of them held subprime
mortgages in recent years.
Mortgages that were
issued against subprime borrowers.
And
a lot
of these securities that were rated
very highly by the rating agencies
rated triple A
ended up defaulting
and losing money for their
investors. And the investors were
all over the world. The United
States is a leader in
mortgage finance. And
it was issuing
companies in the United States
were issuing, not just Fannie
and Freddie, but lots of companies were
issuing mortgage securities
that had triple A ratings.
Which meant that Moody's
and Standard and Poor's and the other
rating agencies were telling you
basically there was no risk to them.
And so people in Europe,
in Asia were investing in these.
And they thought they were perfectly
safe. And then they went
under.
And part
of it was bad faith dealings
by some of the issuers. Some of the
issuers
themselves doubted that these mortgages
were so safe. But
what do I care?
This is what happened. Somebody
originated, it's gotten to be
a complicated set of steps.
Somebody
originates the mortgage. That
means I talk to the homeowner, I
have the homeowner fill out the papers.
Then after they've originated the
mortgage, they sell it to
an investor,
like Fannie or Freddie or some private
mortgage securitizer.
And the private
mortgage securitizer finds
a mortgage servicer, it may be
the originator, who will then
service the mortgage. What does it mean
to service the mortgage? It means
to call you on the
phone if you missed your payment,
for example. Or if you have
questions about the mortgage, there should be someone
you call. So the mortgage servicer
does that. So that's a separate entity.
And then we have the CMO
organizer,
the originator. And then we have the CDO
originator. It's gotten to be a very
complicated financial system.
And then the whole thing collapsed.
So
there's been a lot of reform
to try to see what can we
do to prevent this kind of collapse.
Some people would say, let's
end the whole thing. Let's go back to 1778.
Let's not have mortgage securitizers.
But that's not
the steps that have been taken.
I think that
we are making progress.
And I want to just conclude with
just a little reference to
one important change that
was made in both
Europe and the United States.
So the
European Parliament
passed a
new directive
that requires
or incentivizes
mortgage
originators to keep
5% of the
mortgage balance in their own portfolio.
So that means if you originate
a portfolio, you can sell off
if you originate mortgages,
you can sell off 95%
of the mortgages to investors.
But you have to keep 5%.
So this 5% limit
was then later
incorporated into the Dodd-Frank
Act in the United States.
So we again have the same
requirement.
And this is supposed to
reduce the moral hazard problem
that created
the crisis and retain
the mortgage securitization
process.
So the
idea is this.
I know I heard people tell me,
mortgage originators
sometimes got cynical.
They thought, okay, I'm helping this family
fill out a mortgage,
what do I care?
I think this family doesn't look,
they're not going to pay this back.
But what do I care?
I'll fill it out, I'll sell the mortgage
to someone else and I'm out of here.
In fact, it got bad
in some cases.
Some mortgage brokers, a family would come in
offering to, wanted to buy a house
and the mortgage broker would say that,
well, what is your income anyway?
And
they would tell him the income and he would say,
you're trying to buy a $300,000
house on that income?
I said, I don't know if I can do this.
But then he would say,
wait a minute, think about this again.
Is that really your income?
You told me your income is $40,000
a year. Are you sure?
Don't you have some other, why don't we say
$50,000 a year?
Or I'll say $60,000 a year.
And the mortgage broker would look at him
in disbelief and say,
no, we only have $40,000.
He said, well, think about it.
You have other sources, don't you?
And he said, everybody does this.
So, okay, we have $60,000.
He says, fine.
And he,
and they thought, well, the mortgage broker
gave me permission to do this.
And he doesn't care
because he's not going to take the loss.
So, the new law
is supposed to discourage that kind of thing.
And it has lots of new
laws that are trying to tighten up.
For example, mortgage brokers in the United States
now have to be licensed.
It used to be, just five years ago,
you could be an ex-con, fresh out of jail,
and you could take up a business as
mortgage broker. You can't anymore.
So, what's happening all over the world
is that we've learned from this experience,
but we're retaining this basic
system of mortgage
securitization. Mortgage lenders
that are professional.
The basic industry has been retained.
And we're hoping and thinking
that maybe we have a better system.
So, I will stop there
and I'll see you on Monday.